Guide to the Leopold Haimson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XI: Writings by Others, 1934-1990s
  - Subseries XI.2: Academic and Professional Works, 1934-1990s
    - Raeff, Marc:
      - "Etat, le gouvernement et la tradition politique en Russie Imperiale avant 1861" (Box 155, Folder 12)
      - "Staatsdienst, aussenpolitik, ideologien," 1959 (Box 155, Folder 12)
      - "Well-ordered police state and the development of modernity in seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Europe: an attempt at a comparative approach," 1975 (Box 155, Folder 12)
    - Read, Christopher. "New directions in the Russian intelligentsia: idealists and Marxists in the early twentieth century," 1981 (Box 155, Folder 13)
    - Reid, Alastair:
      - "Division of labour and politics in Britain, 1850-1920" (Box 155, Folder 14)
      - "Labour and society in modern Britain," 1982 (Box 155, Folder 14)
    - Resis, Albert:
      - "Lenin on freedom of the press," 1977 (Box 156, Folder 1)
      - "Spheres of influence in Soviet wartime diplomacy," 1981 (Box 156, Folder 1)
    - Riasanovsky, Nicholas. "Nationality" in the state ideology during the reign of Nicholas I," 1960 (Box 156, Folder 1)
    - Robinson, Geroid. Lectures on Russian history, 1955 (Box 156, Folder 2-7)
    - Rogger, Hans:
      - "Politics, ideology and history in the USSR: the search for coexistence," 1965 (Box 156, Folder 8)
      - "Russia in 1914" (Box 156, Folder 8)
      - "Was there a Russian fascism? The Union of Russian People," 1964 (Box 156, Folder 8)
    - Roosa, Ruth:
      - "Russian industrialists and "State socialism", 1906-17," 1972 (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - "Russian industrialists during World War I: the interaction of economics and politics" (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - "Russian industrialists, politics, and labor reform in 1905," 1975 (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - "United" Russian industry" (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - "Workers insurance and the indusrialistists in the Third State Duma," 1973 (Box 156, Folder 9)
    - Rosenberg, Arthur. "Histoire du bolchevisme," 1967 (Box 157, Folder 1)
    - Rosenthal,k Bernice:
      - "Nietzsche in Russia: the case of Merezhkovsky," 1974 (Box 157, Folder 1)
      - "Theatre as church: the vision of the mystical anarchists," 1977 (Box 157, Folder 1)
      - "Transmulation of the symbolist ethos: mystical anarchism and the Revolution of 1905," 1977 (Box 157, Folder 1)
    - Rothman, Stanley. "Portrait of the Jew as radical" (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Rowland, Richard. "Further investigation of urbanization and industrialization in pre-revolutionary Russia," 1974 see Lewis, Robert
    - Rush, Myron. "Soviet policy and international tension" (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Russian Review: an American quarterly devoted to Russia past and present, 1985 vol.44, #3 (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Rustow, Dankwart. "Communism and change" (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Sakharov, Andrei. "Letter to Brezhnev," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 3)
    - Schapiro, Leonard. "Role of the Jews in the Russian revolutionary movement," 1961 (Box 157, Folder 3)
    - Sevcenko, Ihor:
      - "Muscovy's conquest of Kazan: two views reconciled," 1967 (Box 157, Folder 4)
      - "On some sources of Prince Svjatoslav's Izbornik of the year 1076," 1966 (Box 157, Folder 4)
      - "Two varieties of historical writing," 1969 (Box 157, Folder 4)
    - Serouse, Richard. "Social democracy and the working class to 1905," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 4)
    - Shapiro, Joel. "Russian nobility 1905-1907" (Box 157, Folder 4)
    - Shchetinina, G.I. "Intelligentsiia, revoliutsiia, samoderzhavie (osveshchenie problemy v amerikanskoi burzhuaznoi istoriografii)," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 5)
    - Shelokhaev, V.V. "Agrarnaia programma kadetov v pervoi russkoi revoliutsii," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 5)
    - Shiokawa, Nobuaki:
      - "Collectivization of agriculture and Otkhodnichestvo in the USSR, 1930," 1982-83 (Box 157, Folder 6)
      - "Some aspects of Japanese studies on Russian and Soviet history" (Box 157, Folder 6)
    - Shulman, Marshall:
      - "Future of the Soviet-American competition," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 7)
      - "Four decades of irrationality: U.S.-Soviet relations" (Box 157, Folder 7)
      - "Relations with the Soviet Union" (Box 157, Folder 7)
      - "Superpowers: dance of the dinosaurs," 1987/88 (Box 157, Folder 7)
    - Siegelbaum, Lewis. "Another "Yellow peril': Chinese migrants in the Russian Far East and the Russian reaction before 1917," 1978 (Box 157, Folder 8)
    - Sobolev, G.L.:
      - "Istochnikovedenie i sotsial'no-psikhologicheskoe issledovanie epokhi Oktiabria," 1971 (Box 157, Folder 8)
      - "Pis'ma v Petrogradskii sovet rabochikh i soldatskikh deputatov kak istochnik dlia izucheniia obshchestvennoi psikhologii v Rossii v 1917 g.," 1968 (Box 157, Folder 8)
    - Sontag, John:
      - "International communism and Soviet foreign policy," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 8)
      - "Tsarist debts and tsarist foreign policy," 1968 (Box 157, Folder 8)
    - Stern, Fritz:
      - "Maturing of the nation-state," 1962 (Box 157, Folder 9)
      - "Money, morals, and the pillars of Bismarck's society," 1970 (Box 157, Folder 9)
    - Stites, Richard. "Women's liberation movements in Russia, 1900-1930," 1973 (Box 157, Folder 9)
    - Story, James. "Mysticism and politics: Berdiaev and the Revolution of 1905" (Box 157, Folder 9)
    - Surh, Gerald. "1905 in St. Petersburg: labor, society, and revolution"
      (unpublished manuscript)
      - Version 1 (Box 157, Folder 10-13)
      - Version 1 (cont.) (Box 158, Folder 1-4)
      - Version 2 (Box 158, Folder 5)
        (incomplete: pages 474-547 and 559-672)
    - Thomas, Keith. "Crises and sequences in the political development of England," 1968 (Box 158, Folder 6)
    - Treml, Vladimir. "Input-output analysis and Soviet planning," 1967 (Box 158, Folder 6)
    - Ulam, Adam:
      - "Cold War according to Kennan" (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - "Communist doctrine and Soviet diplomacy," 1970 (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - "Lenin: his legacy," 1970 (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - "Reflections on the revolution," 1967 (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - "USA: some critical reflections," 1964 (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - "Uses of revolution," 1968 (Box 158, Folder 7)
    - Valkenier, Elizabeth:
      - "New Soviet views on economic aid," 1970 (Box 158, Folder 8)
      - "Peredvizhniki and the spirit of 1860s," 1975 (Box 158, Folder 8)
    - Volobuev, P.V. "Proletariat - gegemon sotsialisticheskoi revoliutsii," 1970 (Box 158, Folder 8)
    - Von Laue, Theodore:
      - "Of the crises in the Russian polity," 1963 (Box 158, Folder 9)
      - "Vitte System" in mid-passage," 1896-1899 (Box 158, Folder 9)
      - "Westernization, revolution and the search for a basis of authority - Russia in 1917," 1967 (Box 158, Folder 9)
    - Walker, Edward: see Almond, Gabriel
    - Ward, Chris. "Leningrad textile workers c.1921-1928," 1981 (Box 158, Folder 10)
    - Warshofsky Lapidus, Gail. "Ethnonationalism and political stability: the Soviet case," 1984 (Box 158, Folder 10)
    - Weiner, Douglas. "Community ecology in Stalin's Russia: "Socialist" and "Bourgeois" science," 1984 (Box 158, Folder 10)
    - Williams, Robert. "Russians in Germany: 1900-1914," 1966 (Box 158, Folder 11)
    - Wolfe, Bertram. "New gospel according to Khrushchev," 1960 (Box 158, Folder 11)
    - Woloch, Isser. "Revolution, war, and public assistance: the French Revolution and its veterans," 1983 (Box 158, Folder 11)
    - Wortman, Richard:
      - "Biography and the Russian intelligentsia," 1985 (Box 158, Folder 11)
      - "Judicial personnel and the court reform of 1864," 1969 (Box 158, Folder 11)
    - Yaney, George. "War and the evolution of the Russian state," 1967 (Box 158, Folder 12)
    - Zagoria, Donald. "Ecology of peasant communism in India," 1971 (Box 158, Folder 12)
    - Zeitlin, Jonathan. "Engineers and compositors: a comparison," 1981 (Box 158, Folder 12)
    - Zelnik, Reginald. "Populists and workers: the first encounter between populist students and industrial workers in St. Petersburg, 1871-74," 1972 (Box 158, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified:
      - "Demograficheskie protsessy evreiskogo naseleniia Rossii" (Box 159, Folder 1)
        (based on governors' reports. Also includes data and description of archival funds in Russian archives)
      - "Economic development, the workers' movement and the industrialists of Moscow and the central industrial region of Imperial Russia, 1910-1914" (Box 159, Folder 2)
      - "Geopolitical context of Russian foreign policy 1700-1917" (Box 159, Folder 3)
      - "Law of Marxian socialism," 1962 (Box 159, Folder 4)
      - "Mensheviks and the question of power in 1917" (Box 159, Folder 5-6)
      - "Singing revolution" (Box 159, Folder 7)
      - "Vie quotedienne des paysans sovietique sous la NEP" (Box 159, Folder 8)
      - Untitled incompleted manuscripts:
        - Chapter II: Labor relations: the Soviet, the workers and the industrialists (Box 159, Folder 9)
        - Chapter IV: Toward a coalition government (Box 159, Folder 10)
        - Chapter V: In the Provisional government: social and economic policies (Box 159, Folder 11)
        - Chapter VI: Revolutionary Defensists in power: torn between coalition and the "Camp of democracy" (Box 160, Folder 1)
        - Conclusion: some speculations about the determinants of estate and class consciousness (Box 160, Folder 2)
        - [On strikes] (Box 160, Folder 3-4)
        - Untitled (Box 160, Folder 5)
- Series XII: CVs and Photographs, 1960s-1990s
  This series holds Haimson's CVs and photographs.
  - Haimson's CVs, 1960s-1990s (Box 160, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated, (5 black and white prints) (Box 160, Folder 7)
- Series XIII: Maps, 1900s
  (shelved at RBML Historical Map Collection P-Europe--Russia)
  There are four maps: Karta zheleznykh dorog Evropeiskoi Rossii, Plan Gatchiny, Plan Petergofa, and Plan Sestroretska.
  - Karta zheleznykh dorog Evropeiskoi Rossii, 1904, (14 1/8" x 11")
  - Plan Gatchiny, 1900s, (14 ¾" x 11 ¾")
  - Plan Petergofa, 1900s, (13 1/8" x 11 ¾")
  - Plan Sestroretska, 1900s, (16 ½" x 11 ¾")
- Series XIV: Audio Materials, 1960s
  The series comprises reel-to-reel tapes with materials from the Menshevik Project and some tapes that may not be related to it. Arranged in 3 subseries.
  - Subseries XIV.1: Memoir Reading
    N. Zhordania's memoirs read by I.Zhordania.
    - Zhordania, Noah. Memoirs, (1 reel) (Box 161)
  - Subseries XIV.2: Interviews
    Includes interviews with Georgian Mensheviks and reels entitled "Russian interviews" that may not be related to the Menshevik project. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Arsenidze, Razhden. Interviews #1-5, (5 reel-to-reels) (Box 161)
    - Eradze, Georgii. Interviews #5-8; 11-18, (6 reel-to-reels) (Box 161)
    - Tsuladze, Vasilii. (Box 161)
    - Zhordania, Inna, (3 reel-to-reels) (Box 161)
    - Russian interviews of 1968, (9 reel-to-reels) (Box 162)
  - Subseries XIV.3: Seminars
    Audio records of five seminars. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1962 Schwarz seminar of December 18: Discussion of "Osnovnaia kontseptsiia revoliutsii", (1 reel-to-reel) (Box 161)
    - 1964
      - Lande seminar of January, 25: Discussion of his work, (1 reel-to-reel) (Box 161)
      - Denike seminar of April 11: Discussion of his work, (2 reel-to-reels) (Box 161)
      - Volin seminar of May 2: Discussion of chapters 6 and 7 of his work, (1 reel-to-reel) (Box 161)
    - 1968 Untitled seminar of May 20, (1 reel-to-reel) (Box 162)
- Series XV: Digital Files
  384 of 5.25'' diskettes and 14 of 3.5" diskettes contain files in Lotus 1-2-3, Word and other formats with archival and bibliographical material, manuscripts, letters, papers, statistics, grants and working files mostly related to the Strikes Project. Also contains material related to the Menshevik project, the Russian Exchange program, and various other subjects.
  - Archival and bibliographical material, manuscripts, letters, papers, statistics, grants and working files mostly related to the "Strikes" project but also contain material from Menshevik project, Russian Exchange program, and other various subjects (Box 163-165)
- Series XVI: Oversize Materials, 1920-1969
  Oversize materials removed from Series III: Menshevik Project and stored in flat boxes. Organized into two subseries.
  - Subseries XVI.1: Menshevik Documents
    Includes documents on English delegation of 1920 and research and reference material. Arranged by the type of document.
    - Meetings abroad, past 1917 English delegation: documents, 1920, (photocopies) (Box 166)
    - Reference and research material
      - Chernov, Viktor. "K istorii partii sotsialistov-revoliutsionerov." Russkaia mysl', December 21, 1967-January 11, 1968, (newspaper clippings) (Box 167, Folder 1)
      - Iakubovich, Mikhail. "Pis'mo General'nomu Prokuroru SSSR." Novoe russkoe slovo, October 11, 1969, (newspaper clipping) (Box 167, Folder 2)
  - Subseries XVI.2: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik
    Contains galley proofs and final revises with holograph notes. In chronological order.
    - Editorial materials, (galley proofs and final revises with holograph notes)
      - 1956 #9 (Box 167, Folder 3)
      - 1957 #1-8; 11-12 (Box 167, Folder 4-12)
      - 1958 #1-9; 11-12 (Box 168, Folder 1-10)
      - 1959 #1-3 (Box 169, Folder 1-2)
      - 1962 #11-12 (Box 169, Folder 3)
      - 1963 #1-2; 7-8 (Box 169, Folder 4-6)
      - 1964 Sbornik #1 and 2 (Box 169, Folder 7-8)